<tool id="ou_presto" name="PRESTO Permutation" version="1.0">
    <description>of BEAGLE data</description>
    <command>
        java -jar ${__tool_data_path__}/shared/jars/presto/presto.jar out=out missing=${missing_allele_code} trait=${input_trait_file}
        #if ($input_strata_file != "none"):
            strata=${input_strata_file}
        #end if
        test=$assocs.strip(',')
        topranks=$topranks
        seed=$seed
        nperms=$nperms
        threshold=$threshold
        diplotypes=$diplotypes
        #for $i, $s, in enumerate($input_files):
            ${s.input}
        ;
        mv out.log ${log}
        ;
        mv out.null ${null}
        ;
        mv out.pval ${pval}
    </command>

    <inputs>
        <repeat name="input_files" title="BEAGLE Input File">
            <param name="input" type="data" format="bgl" label="BEAGLE file"/>
        </repeat>

        <param name="input_trait_file" type="data" format="txt" label="Trait file" help="Contains the affection status for each allele. If this contains marker data it will need to be added above also." optional="false"/>

        <param name="missing_allele_code" type="text" label="Missing Allele Code" help="The value given for alleles that are not known." optional="false"/>

        <param name="input_strata_file" type="data" format="txt" label="STRATA file" help="Contains the strata data. If this contains marker data it will need to be added above also." optional="true"/>

        <param name="assocs" type="select" display="checkboxes" multiple="True" label="Association Tests to perform" >
            <option value="t" selected="True">Allelic Trend Test</option>
            <option value="a">Allelic Test</option>
            <option value="r">Recessive Test</option>
            <option value="d">Dominant Test</option>
            <option value="o">Overdominant Test</option>

        </param>

        <param name="topranks" type="integer" value="1" label="Number of Order Statistics" />

        <param name="seed" type="integer" value="-9999" label="Seed value for the random number generator" />

        <param name="nperms" type="integer" value="1000" label="Number of permutations of  the affection status" help="A value of 0 will skip permutation testing"/>

        <param name="threshold" type="float" value="0.0" label="Threshold for Second Stage" help="Determines significance levels for two-stage genotyping designs using the first-stage samples suggested by Frank Dudbridge."/>

        <param name="diplotypes" type="boolean" truevalue="true" falsevalue="false" checked="true" label="Diplotypes?" help="If ticked, the trait status is permuted for the individuals so that both alleles for each individual have the same permuted trait status." />

    </inputs>

    <outputs>
        <data name="log" format="txt" type="data"/>
        <data name="pval" format="txt" type="data"/>
        <data name="null" format="txt" type="data"/>
    </outputs>

    <help>
        This tool performs permutation and association testing using PRESTO as developed by Browning and Browning. More detail can be found here: www.faculty.washington.edu/browning/presto/presto.html.

-----
        **Required arguments**


        *missing allele code* 

        the character or sequence of characters used to represent a missing allele (e.g. missing=-1 or
        missing=0 or missing=?). The missing argument is required. If your data set has
        no missing alleles then set the missing parameter to any character or sequence of
        characters that is not used as an allele.


        *trait file*

        The BEAGLE file containing the affection status for each allele. The affection status is
        specified on a single line beginning with the characte\r “A”. All alleles must have
        an affection status specified. If the file specified with the trait parameter contains
        marker data, the file must also be specified in the genotype data file list (file1
        file2... If the file specified with the trait
        argument contains multiple affection status lines (i.e. lines whose first field is “A”),
        then only the first affection status line will be used. The trait argument is required.


        **Optional arguments**


        *strata file* 
        
        is the BEAGLE file containing the population stratum for each allele. The population stra-
        tum for each allele is specified on a single line beginning with the character “S”. If
        the strata argument is used, all alleles must have a population stratum specified.
        If the file specified with the strata parameter contains marker data, the file must
        also be specified in the genotype data file list (file1 file2 ...). If the file specified with the strata argument contains multiple
        population stratum lines (i.e. lines whose first field is “S”), then only the first pop-
        ulation stratum line will be used. The strata argument is optional. If it is omitted,
        all alleles are assumed to belong to a single population stratum.


        *tests*

        t = allelic trend test
        a = allelic test
        r = recessive test (groups major allele homozygotes and heterozygotes)
        d = dominant test (groups minor allele homozygotes and heterozygotes)
        o = overdominant test (groups minor and major allele homozygotes).
        If the allelic trend test (t) is specified, a 2 × 3 genotype contingency table is
        constructed for each stratum and the Mantel trend test is performed [6]. The Mantel
        trend test is a generalization to stratified data of the allelic trend test [8]. When
        there is only one population stratum, the Mantel trend test is equal to the standard
        allelic trend test after multiplying by N/(N − 1) where N is the sample size.
        For the remaining tests (a, r, d, or o) a 2 × 2 contingency table is constructed
        for each stratum and the Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test with continuity correction
        is performed. The Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test is a generalization to strat-
        ified data of the standard chi-square test of independence. When there is only
        one population stratum, the Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test statistic is equal to the
        standard χ2 test statistic after multiplying by N/(N − 1) where N is the sample
        size. Although, the Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test can be used to test for allelic
        effects (test=a), the Mantel trend test (test=t) is the preferred allelic test since it
        is robust to departure from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium.
        The test statistic for each marker is the maximum χ2 statistic (maximized over
        the specified allelic and genotypic tests). If a marker has more than two alleles,
        each allele is tested for association with affection status by grouping the other al-
        leles. Thus a triallelic marker is tested as if it were three diallelic markers, and
        will result in 3 test statistics. The test argument is optional. The default value is
        test=t. Only the allelic test (test=a) is permitted when diplotypes=false. See
        the diplotypes argument in this section for more details.


        *seed value*

        is an integer seed for the random number generator. The seed argument is optional. The default value is seed=-99999.
        The seed for the random number generator determines the sequence of permutations
        of the trait status. The seed parameter can be used to parallelize an analysis.


        *number of permutations*

        is a nonnegative integer giving the number of permutations of the affection status that will
        be used. You can skip permutation testing by setting nperms=0. The nperms argu-
        ment is optional. The default value is nperms=1000. The computational time for
        permutation testing is linear in the number of permutations. Typically 1,000, or
        10,000 permutations are used to determine experiment-wide statistical significance.


        *number of order statistics*

        is a nonnegative integer giving the number order statistics that will be written to
        the null p-value file. For each marker and permutation of the
        trait status, the test statistic is the maximum χ2 statistic from the association tests
        specified with the test parameter. For each permutation, the test statistics are
        sorted in decreasing order, and the largest topranks test statistics are written to
        the null p-value file. The topranks argument is optional. The default value
        is topranks=1.


        *threshold for 2nd stage* 

        a non-negative floating point number giving the minimum first-stage test statistic
        required for a marker to be genotyped in the second stage of a two-stage genotyping
        design. For each permutation and for each diallelic marker, data from one-half of
        the cases and one-half of the controls is used to calculate the test statistic. If the test
        statistic is greater than or equal to the threshold parameter then the test statistic
        is recalculated using the data from the entire sample.
        The threshold argument is used to determine significance levels for two-stage
        genotyping designs using the first-stage samples as suggested by Frank Dudbridge. 
        The p-value file is not produced when the threshold parameter is set
        greater than 0.0.
        The test statistics in the null p-value file can be used to determine signif-
        icance for any of the top k ranks in your two-stage study where k is equal to the
        topranks parameter. The threshold argument is optional. The default value is
        threshold=0.0 which corresponds to a one-stage genotyping design.


        *diplotypes* 

        is true if the alleles from the same individual are always paired in the PRESTO input file so that the third and fourth
        columns are the alleles for the first individual, the fifth and sixth columns are the
        alleles for the second individual, and so on, and true/false is false if the alleles
        are not paired. The diplotypes options controls how the trait status is permuted
        during permutation testing. If diplotypes=true, the trait status is permuted for
        the individuals so that both alleles for each individual have the same permuted
        trait status. When diplotypes=false, the trait status is permuted for the alle-
        les (rather than for the individuals). Only the allelic test can be performed when
        diplotypes=false (see the test parameter in this section). The diplotypes ar-
        gument is optional. The default value is diplotypes=true.

    </help>

</tool>

